Okay, don't be number six, all about testing and assessment.
Okay, don't be number six, all about testing and assessment. And we've learned how
it's important to really have every control address two things, right? Functional
and assurance, those are the two very important pillars that every control needs to be supported
by. And so this domain obviously is focused on the assurance part. How do we provide assurance
to our stakeholders that first of all security is contributing towards goals and objectives,
but also that we have the right level of security built into certain architectures like applications
and the network and really anything that provides value to the organization. That's what we're
focusing on in this domain. And obviously the best way to address that assurance is through testing
and assessment that the security function has to be focused on and involved in. Yeah, we've got
a little slide here, not some you need to know for the exam, but I think it highlights an important
point, which is our systems are getting unbelievably complex and we are, you know, businesses are incredibly
reliant on these systems to perform business functions. And so we've got a little slide here that
talks about this, the numbers down the side here are the number of lines of code. It's not a great
measure, but it's a way of thinking about just how complex of a system, obviously the more
lines of code, the more complex the system. And then we've got what they line up to here. So what do
you think 50,000 lines of code? What's what does that line up to? Yeah, I would say an average
iPhone app. Yeah, that's your average iPhone app. Now what about 6.5 million lines of code? Yeah,
I don't like that number, but probably Boeing avionics. Yeah, they're excellent systems that have
been working perfectly. 50 million lines of code. Yeah, that'd be Microsoft Windows. Yeah, which
highlights something important. I mean, all of us are our applications run on top of operating
systems. And Windows is not unique in being around 50 million lines of code, but that highlights
just how insanely large and complex these systems are. And if you want a secure system that's going
to be reliable, have integrity, et cetera, it needs to be working properly. And when you have 50
million lines of code, is there is there possibly going to be one or two bugs? I don't know, John,
has there ever been a bug found in Microsoft's code? None of them I can think of. And then so
then what's two billion lines of code? That's Google services. So I mean, this is just a way of showing
you in high level terms, just how complex our systems are. And we need these systems to be working
properly, which is why we need to test them. And so here's a question right that people have
seen. What's the purpose of testing and assessing these architectures, applications, and so on. And
obviously it is to provide assurance to our stakeholders that the right level of security is in those
valuable assets of the organization, right? But testing needs to involve security. We're not just
testing for functionality, we're testing for security functionality as well. As you love to call it
non-functional testing. Yeah, drives as crazy as security professionals. Security often gets called
non-functional testing. It's getting lumped in with that, which whenever projects, you know,
behind schedule over budget, what testing are you not going to do? Oh, don't bother doing the
non-functional stuff. Well, to me, non-functional are not two words that you can put together. I mean,
non-functional, what does that mean? It means it's not functioning. And definitely security is
something that has to function. And so we should never relate to security as anything other than
functionality that is very valuable and important, exactly. And so when we talk about security assessment
and testing, you know, what are we talking about? Where are we doing it? Are we just doing it when
we're developing a system? And the answer is no. I mean, testing is throughout the entire lifecycle
the system. It starts right from the very earliest of the conception of what you might be building
through the entire lifecycle, even, you know, through obviously build and then operation. And even
at the end of the lifecycle, when an application is no longer needed, you've got to test to make sure
you just securely destroy the data. Or have you moved it on to the next system properly? So security
assessment and assessing is involved throughout the entire process. Yeah, not just development,
but the entire lifecycle. So next slide talks about validation and verification. What's the difference?
Yeah. So these are some words you might see. So validation is at the very start.
Validation is this concept that when someone first says, let's build an application or a system,
the first thing you have to understand is what does someone actually want to build? What are the
business requirements? Because if you don't understand what the product is, you can never possibly
build it properly and especially include the right security controls. If you only find out once it's
in production that, oh, hey, by the way, there's some credit card data in there. Oh, okay. Now we've
got to include all the PCI controls. Don't worry, there's only a thousand of those. So validation is
about how do you validate that you've truly understood the business requirements? That you gathered
them all, captured them correctly, and they cover all the requirements. So that's why I like to
refer to as are you building the right product? Have you truly understood what it is that you're supposed
to be building? And then verification is everything that follows that. Once you start actually building
the system and building the security controls into it, you want to make sure you're the product,
you're building the product right. Doesn't actually work correctly as it was designed. Do all the
security controls that you're implementing, you're verifying that those security controls are actually
working correctly. Yeah. And I think we have to relate this to security, right? Validation and
verification needs to be applied to what security does in the overall architecture or system that we're
building. So next up, an important part of validation and just testing in general is that can we ever
be 100% certain that a piece of software is working correctly? The answer is no. Yeah.
It's impossible. I used to do a lot of programming. There was some lines of code where I couldn't even
tell you if a single line of code was working correctly. So we can never be 100% certain. Instead,
this is where we have this concept of you want to develop a level of confidence. You want to be,
you know, do you want to be just like, yeah, sure, good enough or do you want to be like really
certain it's working correctly? So what would drive that, John? What would make you decide? I want to
be really, really confident this is working correctly. Well, you have to understand the requirements
from a stakeholder perspective. So the owner's management, whoever it is that your stakeholder is,
that you're building this for, you need to understand the requirements, but also how security fits in.
And how valuable the system is, the organization, right? The more valuable the system, the more sure
you want to be that it's working correctly. So then as part of verification, are we building the
product right? This is where we talk about the three C's. What are these all about? Yeah, you see
that here, completeness, right? Means exactly that. Let's make sure that we cover everything.
Correctness is accuracy, integrity, and so on. And consistency means that the system works
properly from a security perspective, from start to finish. It's consistently addressing the
security requirements. These are things that you want to verify are not only built in as far as
the product itself, but also operating that way once we're using it. And we can use these when
we're developing test cases, right? completeness, how do we have test cases that cover everything,
correctness to each test case? Look at the right stuff and consistency or all the test cases
consistent from one to the next. Is that kind of the idea? Yes, absolutely. Perfect.
And then next question, how do we decide how much effort do we invest in testing?
Well, this is an answer that everybody should know by now. It's always based on the value that
it represents to the organization. Value is what drives security, including the testing that we do
to prove to stakeholders that security is contributing value. When we look at testing strategies at
at a really high level, how do we go about testing things? There's kind of three major ways
we can go about this. We can do internal testing, which means if it's, let's say we're talking about
Acme Corporation, internal testing would be Acme's own auditors looking at Acme's own systems.
It's all internal. External would be Acme, for instance, looking at one of their service providers.
And actually, I'll spend one second on external here because there's sometimes questions on the test
that kind of befubble people. External can actually mean two different things.
External could be where Acme's own internal auditors are looking at a service provider. That's
external to them. Or it could be that way around. Let's say that Acme is developing a system,
and the upper management doesn't quite have the confidence that their internal people know
quite what they're doing. And they want an outsider's opinion, someone external to the organization
to take a look at things. And so that can be the other definition of external, where someone
like an external auditor is looking in. And then third party obviously implies there are three
parties involved. So this is usually where you have a service provider, like a big cloud provider,
like say, as you are, they will have millions of customers, hundreds of thousands of customers.
And they don't want to have to have every single one of those customers audit them individually.
So they'll hire a trusted third party audit firm to conduct an audit, produce a report,
which then gets handed out to all of their customers. We'll talk about that in a lot more detail
later on, but those are the three parties consumer service provider and the external auditor.
Next slide talks about the role of security in testing. And one of the things that we have to
remember is that, you know, testing should be done by the stakeholders that are involved in
providing assurance towards. And so security really needs to be part of the entire teams.
But the teams also need to include the owners and management and possibly some others
that have a stake in understanding that security is contributing towards value and working
properly as far as the testing that we do. And the key part here is it's not security is not
actually conducting the testing. What's what's security doing? Well, we're monitoring,
but we're also providing assurance from a security perspective. Yeah, we're advising,
we're looking at the results and that's sort of the role of the security professional.