In the last few videos, we've talked through some very technical types of attacks.
We've talked about cross-site scripting, we've talked about sequel injection,
and later on, we'll even talk about buffer overflows. I want to talk about a very simple way to prevent these types of attacks,
because what all of these attacks have to do with these attacks?
In the last few videos, we've talked through some very technical types of attacks.
We've talked about cross-site scripting, we've talked about sequel injection.
Later on, we'll even talk about buffer overflows.
What all of these attacks fundamentally rely on is a system that is vulnerable, and what do I mean by that?
It's a system that is accepting input from a user and storing that input that it should never be accepting and storing.
This is why, and remember this, drill this into your head, the root of all evil for these types of attacks,
like cross-site scripting, sequel injection, buffer overflows, is that it's inadequate data validation.
We're not properly validating what users input. We're not sanitizing their input, and we're not cleaning up their input.
The root of all evil is inadequate data validation.
So how do we fundamentally fix problems like cross-site scripting and sequel injection and buffer overflows input validation?
So here's a big hint for the exam. You will very likely see very technical questions on things like cross-site scripting.
The solution to how you fix these very technical types of attacks is typically very simple.
Validate the user's input. If you do not allow JavaScript code to be sent, stored on the server,
and then re-display to users, you prevent all of these problems from occurring.
If you don't take sequel code and then send it directly to the database, you prevent sequel injection.
If you don't allow input that's too large for the buffer, you don't allow buffer overflows to occur.
So the simple answer you're going to look for on the exam to how you solve these very technical types of attacks is input validation.
Now it might be phrased in different ways and often in more technical ways.
But fundamentally, any answer that says you're sanitizing the input, you're cleaning up the input.
You're somehow validating what the user provides, that's input validation, and that's the answer you should look for.
And one final piece I'll talk about here. This whole section is about how do we secure web-based applications.
And I'll show this diagram. I've shown a number of times now.
And that is the one of the best ways of securing a system is to harden the system.
Go through a well-defined set of steps, a baseline, to lock that system down.
Disable unnecessary services, closed unused ports, all that sort of stuff.
That's how we secure our web-based applications.