Vulnerability Analysis
Why do we conduct Vulnerability Assessments or...
Why do we conduct Vulnerability Assessments or pen tests?
The whole purpose of doing this is to identify potential or real vulnerabilities in a system.
Let's bring this back to Risk Analysis, which we've talked about.
The very first thing we want to do in Risk Analysis is identify our assets.
We then want to identify the threats that those assets might be susceptible to,
that we might have a significant exposure to.
To identify threats we use, threat modeling.
The piece that we haven't talked about yet is how do we identify the vulnerabilities,
the weaknesses that may exist in a system.
That's what Vulnerability Analysis is all about.
How do we identify the vulnerabilities in a system?
Now, there's two kind of major types of vulnerability analysis we can do.
There's vulnerability assessments, and there are pen tests, penetration testing.
What's the difference?
Well, they share a lot in common.
Both of them, you have to have a very clearly defined scope of exactly what it is that you're going to be assessing.
You should have a schedule, so you know when you're going to be doing it.
A great example of this.
It's not uncommon to break or damage or harm systems when you're conducting these types of tests,
so you typically don't want to do these in the middle of the holiday shopping season,
or it's your busiest time.
You often want to schedule these things to do them in a certain time of day
where it's going to have the least impact if you accidentally negatively affect a system.
You absolutely want to attain approval.
Now, let me share a quick story of this, okay?
There's a real story from one of my former clients.
They hired a Gung Ho new security tester, and this young fellow really wanted to prove
that he was a go-getter and that he was going to be, you know, he was going to be a quick riser
of the latter within his company.
And so he wanted to prove that he was very proactive.
And so on day one, he, of the fifth job, first aid being on the job, he downloaded Nessus.
He installed it on his system.
He figured out the IP addresses of the corporation's systems.
And for this corporation, 80% of their infrastructure was in AWS, the Amazon Web Services Cloud.
And so he decided to scan their systems in AWS, figured out the right IP addresses,
typed those into Nessus, chose aggressive scan and hit go.
What did AWS do?
Well, AWS gets hit by attacks all the time because an aggressive vulnerability scan
looks like someone's trying to attack your systems.
And unless you have specific permission, AWS doesn't necessarily allow you to scan their infrastructure.
And so AWS blocked this corporation's IP address.
And their entire IP address range just blocked it.
80% of this company's systems were in AWS.
How long did it take them to get those systems unblocked, to get their IP addresses unblocked
so they could access their cloud services?
80% of their IT infrastructure?
Four days.
So this company couldn't access any of their IT systems for four days.
Yeah, that guy was so fired.
So here's a perfect example of where you need to obtain approval for management
from the service provider or whomever you're scanning.
And then they share a lot of the same steps which will go through in a moment
to your enumeration and so forth.
What's the differences, though, between vulnerability assessment and pen testing?
Here's the key difference.
They both start out the same way, which is identifying potential vulnerabilities.
But in a vulnerability analysis, that's where you stop at potential vulnerabilities.
And the key difference is with penetration testing, you attempt to actually exploit those vulnerabilities.
And so that's the key difference between pen testing and vulnerability assessment.
And vulnerability assessment, you stop at potential vulnerabilities and go straight to reporting.
Whereas in a pen test, you identify potential vulnerabilities and then you attempt to exploit them.
And then report.
And so what this kind of boils down to is that vulnerability assessments tend to be more automated.
You can just run an automated tool like Qualess or Necess.
Whereas pen tests tend to be more manual.
You need to know, you need to have someone who knows what they're doing to try and penetrate and break into systems.
And because vulnerability assessments tend to be more automated, they're usually a little faster minutes hours.
Whereas pen tests tend to take more time, maybe days.
Vulnerability assessments tend to be less intrusive.
There's less chance of breaking a system if you're just scanning it for potential vulnerabilities.
If you try and actually exploit, execute those vulnerabilities, there's a good chance you're going to break the system.
And so pen tests tend to be a little more intrusive.
And so that's kind of some of the major key differences between the two of them that you should know about.
Now let's go through the steps that you're going to go through for a pen test or a vulnerability analysis.
And it starts with reconnaissance.
And the defining characteristic of reconnaissance is that it is a passive activity.
And by passive, I mean the organization has no way to detect that this is occurring.
So an attacker or a pen tester that's been hired to do this.
What sort of stuff could they do that could not be detected?
Well, they're looking at publicly available sources of information like DNS records and LinkedIn profiles and job postings.
They're looking for examples of TMI, too much information.
So for instance, in a job posting, if an organization said we require an expert in Oracle version 361,
or a Linux system administrator who's an expert on Susay Linux version 371,
that gives you a lot of information on exactly what version of software and organization is running,
which is very useful information to an attacker.
And so that's what reconnaissance is about.
Passive activity, the organization can't detect it, gathering publicly available information.
Next is enumeration.
In enumeration, enumeration's mathematical term, it means to move systematically through a list one by one.
So what could we move systematically through?
IP addresses and ports.
So if you know an organization has the IP address 1.1.1 and 1.1.1.17,
they probably also have 2 and 3 and 4 and 5 up to 17.
So you could enumerate through IP addresses, and then for each of those IP addresses,
you're going to enumerate through the ports.
We're going to talk about in domain 4.
Ports are services.
And so if you see, for instance, that port 80 is open, that's probably a web server,
because 80 is for web traffic.
4.4.3 is for encrypted SSL web traffic.
So different ports being open equate to different services,
different potential vulnerabilities in the system.
Next is vulnerability analysis.
And this is where you try to identify the exact vulnerabilities that the system might be susceptible to.
And this is why it's so incredibly important to figure out the exact version of an operating system of an application that's running.
Because different systems have different vulnerabilities.
Different versions have different vulnerabilities.
So a big part of vulnerability analysis is figuring out exactly what version of a piece of software is running.
And that's why later on, we're going to talk about figure printing and banner grabbing.
These are methods that you can use to determine the exact version of something that's running,
so that you can then identify the potential vulnerabilities.
And how this works in a scanning tool like Nessus, for instance, is it's a giant database.
And it just lists for this particular version of a system,
here's all the potential vulnerabilities.
And so once Nessus as a scanning tool or qualifies figures out the version of a system that's running,
let's say, here you go, here's your list of potential vulnerabilities.
And so the next step is execution.
But I want to highlight something important here.
If you're doing a vulnerability assessment, you're going to do the reconnaissance,
you're going to do the enumeration, you're going to do the vulnerability analysis,
but you're going to skip execution and go straight to reporting and documenting.
Because execution is where you try to exploit the vulnerabilities.
And it's only in pen testing that we try to actually exploit.
So in vulnerability assessment, we skip over this, but in a pen test,
execution means we attempt to actually exploit the vulnerabilities.
And then the final step is where we document our findings.
In a vulnerability assessment, this is, if you're ever seeing one of these,
like a report on a Nessus out of Nessus, it's not a nice short, pithy document.
These things can be hundreds of pages long.
And one of the real challenges we have, especially the vulnerability assessment,
because you're just identifying potential vulnerabilities,
you can get a lot of false positives.
It's where the scanning tools say, oh, looks like you have this vulnerability in that one,
and that one.
And because it's not in a vulnerability assessment, actually trying to exploit the vulnerabilities,
those are a lot of potential for false positives.
And so a big advantage of a pen test is it helps to eliminate these false positives.
Either way, you've got to document your findings from either of these tests,
put it in context of how valuable these systems of the organization,
and also look at numbers, like we're going to talk about later,
your CVE number, your CVSS number is to help identify exactly what these vulnerabilities are,
and how severe they are.