Testing code for days, weeks on end, that's manual testing done by a person.
Automated testing is where we're using an automated tool.
We're continuing our discussion of various different techniques that we can
use to test software. So in this slide here we're going to talk about different
testing techniques and there's a different sort of categories we're going to go
through and you can mix and match these different tests as I'll explain at
the end after I've provided a simple explanation of each of these. So let's
talk about whether we're doing manual or automated testing. What's the difference?
Well manual testing is some poor soul, change their desk, testing code for days,
weeks on end, that's manual testing done by a person. Automated testing is where
we're using an automated tool like a code scanning tool. So that's manual versus
automated. Run time is about whether the code is actually running. So static testing
means the code is not running, it's static, which means what are we actually
testing here? Well we're looking at the source code itself and we're scanning
through looking for problems in this course in the source code like say not
doing bounds checking. Dynamic testing on the other hand means the code is
running. So this is where the code is essentially a black box. We're feeding
input, we're looking at output, we're seeing how the code responds when it's
running and fuzz testing is actually a form of dynamic testing. And here's how I
like to think about fuzz testing. What would happen if you put a sugar high
four-year-old in front of a computer system and said go crazy, what would they
do? It would be chaos, they'd be slamming on the keyboard, they'd be sticking
baloney in the CD drive, it would be total insanity. That's a pretty good way to
think of fuzz testing. The whole point of fuzz testing is to throw chaos, random,
unexpected input at the system to see how it reacts. And most systems are
probably going to find, you're going to find problems. And the reason for this is
programmers are very logical people. You expect logical input, provides logical
output. When you throw chaos in a system, it tends to cause them to break. I'll
share a fun story about this that I had personally. So I had a, I had a
professor in university who loved to give really brutal assignments like, and give
you like 24 hours notice or something. And so everyone would always be in the
computer lab till like 3 a.m. or something when the assignment was due the
next morning. And he knew this. And he would sometimes come by the computer lab
in the middle of the night when we were all just zombies trying to finish our
code. And he would just walk by someone's keyboard when they were running their
code. And he would just mash his hand into the keyboard. And what would inevitably
happen? Well, the computer would, the program would crash. He was a lovely
fellow. So that's fuzz testing. And then access to code, this refers to whether
or not you have access to the code when you're testing. In black box testing, you
obviously don't have access. It's a black box to you. And in white box testing, it
means you have access to the code. Now we can mix and match these different
things. So for instance, what would be an automated static white box test? Well,
that would be running a code scanning tool like say HP fortify against our source
code. And what about say a manual dynamic black box test? Well, that could be a
pen tester manually trying to find vulnerabilities in the code. So you can
mix and match these to achieve different types of tests. Next, let's talk about
what are known as positive negative and misuse testing. To explain these, let's
think about a login mechanism where you're expected to provide a username and
a password. Positive testing would be if you provided a correct user name and a
correct password, what should the system do? It should log you in. So that means the
system works as expected. Negative testing is for normal errors. What sort of
normal errors would you expect with a login mechanism? Well, I don't know about
you, but whenever I change my password for like the next week, I fat finger my
password, I forget my password. So I incorrectly passed type my password. And what
should the system do? Should it explode? No, it should gracefully error out and say,
you know, something nice like, have you forgotten your password? You would eat
something like that. So that's a normal negative error. You expect those type of
errors. The final type of testing you can do is what's known as misuse testing.
This is where you're looking for someone who's abusing the system. They're
trying to do something that a normal user wouldn't do like say SQL injection. So
these are three types of tests that we can run. Now, a topic that's come up a lot
recently on the exam is what is known as equivalence partitioning and boundary
value analysis. Both of these techniques are used to make our testing more
efficient. Rather than having to test every possible single test case, these two
different techniques allow us to reduce the amount of testing that we do, but
still get good coverage. Still make sure we're testing and making sure that our
code is working correctly. Now, to kind of explain the differences between these
two, let's imagine a input box here where you're supposed to provide a
password between 18 to 16 characters. And we want to check to see if our code is
working correctly, if enhandling to make sure that a password is between eight
and 16 characters. So let's say here's all the possible password links that you
could have between zero and we're going to test up to 24. A very inefficient way
of testing. This is you could test. Okay, what happens if I provide no password?
Does it work properly? What about a password of one? A password of two, three. You
could try each and every single one of these one by one. Do every single test
case. Not very efficient. So the first method that we can use here is what's
known as identifying the boundaries, boundary value analysis. So what are the
boundaries? Well, we have this boundary between seven, eight, and nine characters.
There's a boundary here. If you provide less than eight characters, it should give
you an error. And if you provide eight characters or more, it should allow your
password. So we have a boundary at eight. Where's our second boundary? Well, it
should accept up to and including 16 characters and it should error on more than
16 characters. So we have another boundary here. So boundary value analysis is
about identifying these boundaries and then focusing or testing on either side
of the boundary. So if we want to make sure that our code works, we could test
every possible value, but why not just test the boundaries? So we could test seven
characters and eight characters. And we could test 16 characters and 17
characters. So boundary value analysis is this idea of identifying the boundaries
and testing on either side of the boundary. Equivalent partitioning is the idea
of identifying different partitions. So we've got essentially three partitions
here. We have below seven characters, eight to 16 characters and above 17
characters. So these are our three partitions. And then what we can do is choose
test cases within those partitions. And again, both of these are about trying to
reduce the amount of testing that we do. And here's a quick summary of them. So in
equivalence partitioning, we're dividing our input partitions into groups which
exhibit similar behavior. And in boundary value analysis, we're identifying and
focusing our testing around the boundaries. So I've put together a little
sampling of these different types of tests. So you can see what they look like.
See if you understand what they look like. So we're supposed to provide a
enter a number between zero and nine. So let's say we decide to enter this as our
number. What type of test would that be? Well, I mean, this is an example of
sequel injection. So that would be misuse testing. Okay, what if we were to
provide this? We're supposed to enter a number between zero and nine and we put
in 10. Well, that would be a negative test. It's a normal expected error.
Someone might put in, you know, a character to one the other side accidentally.
Okay, what if we enter the number two? Well, that would be a positive test.
That's normal expected input. What if we put in these nine? If we tested these
individually one by one, we tested negative one, we tested one, we tested eight
and we tested 10. Well, this would be an example of boundary value and
analysis because those numbers are on either side of the boundaries. And then the
final one that we could try here would be say negative five, five and 15.
These are all numbers from our three different partitions. So that would be an
example of equivalent partitioning. Next, let's talk about this concept of test
coverage analysis. And this is simply the idea that when you're testing a piece
of software, you can never test every possible piece of functionality within the
code. And so test, test coverage analysis is simply what percentage of the code
source code is actually covered by our testing. Obviously, the more certain that
you want to be that the code is working properly that there aren't bugs in the
software, you want to be closer and closer to 100% of your source code. But it's
very expensive, very difficult to achieve that. And so what's going to drive the
test coverage analysis that you want to achieve? Well, the more valuable the
system, the more you're going to invest in testing that system and making sure
that it's working properly.