This is thing on, testing, testing, okay.
We just talked about the difference between vulnerability assessments and pen tests, and the
steps that you can go through in these types of tests you can go through, pass analysis, enumeration,
and so forth. Let's now talk about some more detailed types of testing you can do here.
And we're going to talk about different perspectives, different approaches,
different types of knowledge that you can give your pen test or when they're conducting these
types of tests. Let's start with perspective. And by this we mean where is the test, where is the
person that's performing a test located? Internal means they are inside the network.
External means they're conducting a test from outside. So internal would be a test of what happens
if the attacker is inside your network. What can they get to from inside? And external would be a
test from any random person on the internet. What can they get to from out on the internet? What can
they see? When we talk about approaches blind versus double blind, this is about how much information
you give to who? So let's start with blind. Blind means you don't give the person that's or people,
the team that's conducting the security assessment, any information. They are blind. You don't give
them any of the key IP addresses. You don't give them any credentials, nothing like that. You basically
just say, here's the IP address or here's here's the environment we want you to pen test,
to volunteer ability assessment, go at it. And it's there to job the trying to figure out everything
on their own. Double blind is not only do you not give the assessor any information, you also don't
tell the security operations team that are monitoring the network looking for these types of attack.
You don't tell them that the attack is occurring. And so a double blind test is not only a test of
what can the attacker get into. It's also a test of how effectively can the security operations team
detect the attack and respond to the attack? Who would typically approve a double blind test?
Well, not the security assessment team because they don't know what's happening. So this is usually
by senior management, something like that. And finally, knowledge. Knowledge is simply related to
how much knowledge you give the assessor. In zero knowledge, black box testing, you don't give them
any information, which is why I had that connection between blind and black box zero knowledge.
It's the same thing. And then you have partial grain knowledge and full knowledge, give them
full credentials. Now you can mix and match these different tests to achieve different types of
things like an internal full knowledge test. This would be a good test of a malicious insider.
So if you had someone within your own organization that went rogue and they might have the credentials
to all sorts of systems, they have a lot of knowledge, a full knowledge white box test,
and they're inside your network. You could also do, for instance, a black external test. This
would be just some random person on the internet that doesn't know anything about your organization,
trying to break in. So you can mix and match these to achieve different types of tests.
We're now going to talk about automated vulnerability scanners, scanning tools,
likenesses, and callous things like that, and how you can run them in a couple of different modes,
credentialed or un-credentialed. Uncredentialed means you don't give the scanning tool the ability
to log into the system. It's only able to scan the system and see what an outsider could see.
A credentialed scan means you give the scanning tool the ability to actually log into the system
that it's scanning. Give it the ability to log in and check patch levels, check configuration,
that sort of thing. So why would you want to do one of these versus the other? Well, an
un-credentialed scan is a good simulation of someone that doesn't have the credentials to your system,
an outside attacker or even a malicious insider that doesn't have the ability to log in. So what can
the system see if it can't log in? But the problem with an un-credentialed scan is it's typically
going to provide a lot of false positives. The scanner will say, oh, there's a vulnerability here,
but if the scanner was to actually log into the system and check, oh, you know what, there's
actually this patch installed or this configuration change has been made, it might help eliminate
false positives. And so that's one of the big advantages of doing a credentialed scan. The scanning
tool can log into the system, check the exact patch level, the exact configuration level, help to
reduce the false positives. You can also do things like check baselines. So for instance, if you have
a defined baseline of what a good, you know, what a server is supposed to look like, your scanning tool,
if it's doing a credentialed scan can log into that system and check for compliance against the
baseline. So that's a credentialed scan. The big downside with credentialed scans is that you're
giving your scanning tool the credentials to your systems, the ability to log in. And so that's now
another security risk that you have to be concerned with. There are a bunch of different testing
techniques that we can use in conducting vulnerability assessments and pen tests. And there's really
only a couple on the slide that I wanted to dig into a little bit. War dialing and war driving.
What's war dialing? This is the idea that you enumerate through telephone numbers,
looking for a system to pick up. So you try all sorts of different telephone numbers until
instead of getting a, hello, you get a, he, I, I, if I heard that noise, it's a modem. That means
that what picked up on the other end was a computer or a fax machine. So war dialing is a very old
technique. I used to do this in high school. It's still a valid technique, though. And here's why
the most reliable network that's ever been created in the world is the telephone system,
the pot system, the plain old telephone system. It's unbelievably reliable. Even when the powers
out everywhere, lots of lines are down, you pick up an old telephone, you still get a dial tone.
And so if you've got a really critical system that you want a back door into an ability to log
into, even if everything's gone to hell, using a modem is actually a pretty good way of doing
that. And so it's surprising. I've been involved in a number of tests where it never would have
expected. But we've tried this and we've found that there are still modems up and running. And
we've been able to log in through these modems and get into systems. And that highlights why this
is still worth doing because these modems are still out there. And importantly, the people that
set up these modems, they first put this back door in place. Where are they now? You know, they set
this up 30 years ago, 20 years ago, 10 years ago. Maybe they're five feet under, no, it's horrible.
Now, I mean, they're probably not in their role anymore. They're probably not monitoring this
anymore. And so these these old modems tend to get forgotten. So they're still worth looking at.
War driving is the concept of instead of going through telephone numbers you look for,
Wi-Fi access points. That's war driving. They're looking for Wi-Fi access points,
ideally ones that are unencrypted or use web.
Now, a really important thing that we need to do when we're running
have vulnerability assessment is we need to know the exact version of a system that's running.
We need to know exact version of the operating system, exact version of a piece of software,
of a particular application. And the reason it's so important to know the exact version is
different systems are vulnerable to different things. And there's two primary techniques that we
can use to figure out the exact version of a system. The first is known as banner grabbing.
And it's being shown to you here with a picture. Here we've got we've produced an error 404
message that means a file not found on a web server. And you'll see here that the
Aero404 says the exact version of Apache Tomcat that's running. This is a perfect example of
banner grabbing. You produce an error message on the system and as part of that error message on
the system it outputs the exact version of the number of the system. Your systems should never
be configured to do this. There's no reason to tell your internet users what the version of Tomcat
is that's running. You don't even need to tell there's an error for a message because most of them
probably don't even know what that is. So banner grabbing is where the system is far too verbose
in its error reporting. And you just simply from these banners you're able to grab the exact
version number of a system. Fingerprinting is a little more subtle. The way that a system
constructs packets communicates over the network is unique to a particular system. Different operating
systems, different applications, although the OSI model standardizes how systems are supposed
to talk to each other. There are very subtle and slight differences between how different systems
construct packets and communicate. And if you look very carefully at this you can fingerprint
a system. You can try and figure out the exact version of something that's running. Now when it
comes to interpreting and understanding the results produced by your scanning tool. There's a
couple of really important numbers we need to look at. The first is what's known as the CVE
number, common vulnerability and exposure number. What this is is there's a lot of different
scanning tools, vulnerability assessment tools, malware detection tools, IDS, IPS, SIM systems
that we have throughout our environment that might be detecting vulnerabilities or threats in
the environment. And one of the problems that we have is that different firms that detect
a new vulnerability they'll tend to give it a really sexy marketing name like SQL Slammer or
Heartbleed or something like that because it sounds cool. And it's a good way to market you know
all our tool can is able to detect SQL Slammer. That sounds way better than our tool can detect
CVE 2019 0605. So the problem though is that you might have different tools around your environment
that are all reporting different vulnerabilities. This is SQL Slammer. This is Heartbleed.
They're the same thing though. And so the CVE number is meant to be a common number. If a vendor
discovers a vulnerability they need to go and look in the CVE database to see if that vulnerability
already exists. If it does they'll note down the CVE number and they can still give their
vulnerability a sexy marketing term but then they'll also say here's the actual CVE number.
And if they query the database and they find that the CVE that this vulnerability doesn't exist yet
then a new CVE number will be created and everyone else that then subsequently queries the database
will then use that one CVE number. So CVE numbers are meant to give a unique identification number
to vulnerabilities out there so that you can identify the same vulnerability across different vendors.
The second number the CVSS score is in a way is it's a measurement system to try and tell you how
big of a deal is a vulnerability. Is it a collective we don't care or is it run around screaming we're
all going to die. And that's what the CVSS score is. 0 is and 10 is we should all be running screaming.
And so when your vulnerability scanning tool produces a report for you for every vulnerability
identified it should give the CVE number and the CVSS score so you can know exactly what it is
and how big of a deal is this vulnerability. And obviously anything with a higher number you
want to prioritize the remediation activities the patching the configuration whatever that's
going to protect your environment against this really big deal vulnerability.
The final piece I'll talk about here is this concept of false positives and false negatives.
We've talked about this a couple times but just to really reinforce it here it's very calm
and that our scanning tools especially if we're doing an un credentialed vulnerability scan will
produce false positives. The scanning tool will tell us there's a vulnerability here and there
isn't that's a false positive. False negative is the inverse. A false negative is where a scanning
tool says nope everything's good nothing here and there is in fact a vulnerability. So false negatives
are far far worse it's where we get a false sense of security. So we want to try and tune down
and get rid of as many false positives as possible but not to the point of getting false negatives.