Continue in our discussion of testing. Let's now talk about operational testing.
There's three major types of operational testing that we're going to talk about.
Rum, synthetic transactions and progression testing. Let's start with rum.
Rum stands for real user monitoring. Real user monitoring is simply the concept that you watch your log files to see what real users are doing with your system.
Are they when they're accessing your website? Are there certain error messages popping up like 404 or a file mod found or something like that?
So, watching your log files to see how real users are watching your system is known as real user monitoring.
Now, what about synthetic transactions? Synthetic transactions is this idea that we synthesize or we create transactions on a system.
How do we do that? Well, think of it as creating little software scripts or bots.
And these little software scripts or bots will perform certain functions.
So, maybe a good way to think about this is an online banking system.
An online banking system has all sorts of functionality. You can log in. You can check your account balance. You can transfer funds.
You could write synthetic transactions that would test or would perform each of these operations. One of them would log in.
Another would transfer funds. Another would check an account balance.
And if you write a synthetic transaction or a little bot that tests each of these pieces of functionality,
then you can run all those transactions, those synthetic transactions, and see all the functions, for instance, on your website working correctly.
And there's another really cool usage for synthetic transactions. And that is, what if instead of running these one at a time?
What if you were to run 10,000 of them simultaneously? What would that test? Well, that would test load or performance of your application.
See how your application performs if it's getting hit by a whole lack of users like on Black Friday.
So, you can use synthetic transactions to test the performance of your application.
Here's a really good test question that sometimes comes up. What would be the most accurate environment in which you perform synthetic transactions?
And the answer is production. If you truly want to know how your system is going to react to a huge load,
the best environment to test in is production. Are you going to be extremely careful about doing that? Of course.
You're all sorts of testing and dev and so forth, so forth first. But if you truly want to know how your application is going to react, test and production.
The next type of testing we're going to talk about is regression testing.
And regression testing is simply the idea that if you make a change to a system, not only do you want to check to make sure all the new functionalities working correctly,
but also make sure that all the existing functionality keeps working properly.
That is regression testing. It's this concept of testing code or testing systems to make sure you didn't break anything when you implement a change.
With any of the testing that we've talked about in the last few modules, it's important to have very clear test results.
To know, for instance, did your test actually pass or did it fail? You don't want the result of the test to be, eh, maybe.
You wanted to be, yes, it passed or no, it didn't pass. And you want to be able to have the right level of detail in the test results,
the right metrics reported to the right people. The way that you report the results of a test is going to vary depending on who the audience of that test result is and what it is they're looking to see.
We're looking to see.